[
    {
        "question": "Gif monnes (<em>tunge</em>) #### biþ of heafde oðres monnes dadum don, gebete him mid .lx. scill — If a man's tongue is struck from the head by another man's deeds, compensate him with 60 shillings",
        "correctAnswer": "tunge",
        "explanation":"Here 'tunge' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God betæhte þæt mare leoht þæt is seo sunne to þæm dæge ond þæt læsse leoht þæt is se (<em>mona</em>) #### to ðære nihte — God assigned the greater light, that is the sun, to the day, and the lesser light, that is the moon, to the night",
        "correctAnswer": "mona",
        "explanation":"Here 'mona' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>cempa</em>) #### oferwon frecnessa fela — The champion overcame many perils",
        "correctAnswer": "cempa",
        "explanation":"Here 'cempa' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>Culfre</em>) #### is bilewite nyten ond fram geallan biternysse ælfremed — A dove is a meek animal and a stranger to the bitterness of gall",
        "correctAnswer": "culfre",
        "explanation":"Here 'culfre' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ac Albanes slaga ne moste gesundful libban forðam þe him burston ut butu his (<em>eage</em>) #### ond to eorðan feollon mid albanes heafde — But Alban's slayer was not allowed to live in health, because both his eyes burst out of him and fell to the earth with Alban’s head",
        "correctAnswer": "eagan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eage' is both a subject and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eagan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Æt helle duru (<em>draca</em>) #### eardigaþ — Dragons dwell at hell's door",
        "correctAnswer": "dracan",
        "explanation":"Here 'draca' is both the subject and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'dracan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>eage</em>) #### sind flæscene ond teð bænene — Eyes are of flesh and teeth of bone",
        "correctAnswer": "eagan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eage' is both the subject and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eagan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se Halga Gast wæs æteowod ofer Criste on his fulluhte on anre (<em>culfre</em>) #### anlicnysse — The Holy Ghost appears over Christ, at his baptism, in likeness of a dove",
        "correctAnswer": "culfran",
        "explanation":"Here 'culfre' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'culfran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gefyrn scean leoht ingehydes geond þære (<em>eorðe</em>) #### ymbhwyrft —  Of old the light of knowledge shone over the circumference of earth",
        "correctAnswer": "eorðan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eorðe' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eorðan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þonne bið seo sunne be seofonfealdum beorhtre þonne heo nu sy ond se mona hæfð þære (<em>sunne</em>) #### leoht — Then will the sun be sevenfold brighter than it now is, and the moon will have the light of the sun",
        "correctAnswer": "sunnan",
        "explanation":"Here 'sunne' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'sunnan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He ne hierþ nanes (<em>wita</em>) #### word — He didn't hear any advisor's words",
        "correctAnswer": "witan",
        "explanation":"Here 'wita' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'witan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðu fortrydst leona ond (<em>draca</em>) #### — You shall be a treader down of lions and dragons",
        "correctAnswer": "dracena",
        "explanation":"Here 'draca' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'dracena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gelyfde an ðara (<em>cempa</em>) ####, ðæs nama wæs Romanus, and cwæð to þæm Godes cyðere, 'Laurentie, ic geseo Godes engel standende ætforan ðe' — One of the soldiers, whose name was Romanus, believed, and said to the martyr of God, 'Lawrence, I see God's angel standing before thee'",
        "correctAnswer": "cempena",
        "explanation":"Here 'cempa' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'cempena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þara (<em>cnapa</em>) #### ðe binnan syxtyne geara ylde wæron hund-nigontig ðusenda hie tosendon to gehwylcum leodscipum to ðeowte — Of boys who were within sixteen years of age, they sent ninety thousand to all nations in slavery",
        "correctAnswer": "cnapena",
        "explanation":"Here 'cnapa' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'cnapena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Saulus heold ðara leasra (<em>wita</em>) #### reaf ond heora mod to þære stæninge geornlice tihte — Saul held the garments of the false witnesses, and zealously instigated their minds to the stoning",
        "correctAnswer": "witena",
        "explanation":"Here 'wita' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'witena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðas ðry dagas wæron buton seo (<em>sunne</em>) #### ond se monan ond þa steorran ond eallum tidum gelicere wægan mid leohte ond þeostrum aðenede — Those three days were without the sun, the moon, the stars and all the hours, stretched out with light and darkness in equal balance",
        "correctAnswer": "sunnan",
        "explanation":"Here 'sunne' is in the accusative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'sunnan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða het se casere his (<em>hunta</em>) #### hine ðær gefeccean ond hine mid sweorde ofslean — Then the emperor bade his hunters fetch him there and kill him with a sword",
        "correctAnswer": "huntan",
        "explanation":"Here 'hunta' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'huntan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God him sette (<em>nama</em>) #### Adam — God gave him the name Adam",
        "correctAnswer": "naman",
        "explanation":"Here 'nama' is in the accusative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'naman'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða easternan tungelwitegan gesawon niwne (<em>steorra</em>) #### beorhtne — The eastern astronomers saw a new bright star",
        "correctAnswer": "steorran",
        "explanation":"Here 'steorra' is in the accusative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'steorran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þæm ylcan dæge he geworhte ealle (<em>steorra</em>) #### ond tida gesette — On the same day he created all stars and established hours",
        "correctAnswer": "steorran",
        "explanation":"Here 'steorra' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'steorran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God gesceop us twa eagan ond twa (<em>eare</em>) #### twa nosðyrlu twegen weleras twa handa ond twegen fet — God gave two eyes and two ears, two nostrils, two lips, two hands and two feet ",
        "correctAnswer": "earan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eare' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'earan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðær wæron gecype (<em>oxa</em>) #### ond scep ond culfran ond þær sæton myneteras — There were oxen, sheep and doves for sale, and there sat moneyers",
        "correctAnswer": "oxan",
        "explanation":"Here 'oxa' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'oxan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ezechias eac asende his (<em>wita</em>) #### mid hæran gescrydde to þæm witegan Isaiam — Hezekiah also sent his counsellors clad in haircloth to the prophet Isaiah",
        "correctAnswer": "witan",
        "explanation":"Here 'wita' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'witan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He betæhte lamb to his (<em>cnapa</em>) #### ond se cnapa hit ofsloh — He gave a lamb to his boy and the boy slew it",
        "correctAnswer": "cnapan",
        "explanation":"Here 'cnapa' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'cnapan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif ic þisum (<em>draca</em>) #### to forswelgenne geseald eom, hwi sceal ic elcunge þrowian for eowerum oferstealle? — If I am given to this dragon to be swallowed, why should I suffer delay through your presence?",
        "correctAnswer": "dracan",
        "explanation":"Here 'draca' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'dracan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ðe ofer (<em>eorþe</em>) #### geworhte, on ðære ðu scealt yrmþum lifgan — I created you on earth, on which you shall live in misery",
        "correctAnswer": "eorþan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eorþe' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eorþan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ælfred cyning sende þa scipu to þæm (<em>muþe</em>) #### — King Alfred sent the ships to the river-mouth",
        "correctAnswer": "muþan",
        "explanation":"Here 'muþe' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'muþan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Abraham ferde mid twam (<em>cnapa</em>) #### to fyrlenum lande — Abraham went with two boys to a distant land",
        "correctAnswer": "cnapum",
        "explanation":"Here 'cnapa' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'cnapum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Anhyrne deor þæt deor hæfð ænne horn bufan ðæm twam (<em>eage</em>) #### swa strangne and swa scearpne — A one horned deer, that deer has one horn above the two eyes so strong and so sharp",
        "correctAnswer": "eagum",
        "explanation":"Here 'eage' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'eagum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Æfter ðam he gestrynde (<em>sunu</em>) #### ond dohtra — After that he begot sons and daughters",
        "correctAnswer": "suna",
        "explanation":"Here 'sunu' is a u-declension noun in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'a' ending to become 'suna'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Domicianus wearþ acweald æt his witena (<em>hand</em>) #### — Dominic was slain by the hands of his counsellors",
        "correctAnswer": "handum",
        "explanation":"Here 'hand' is a u-declension noun in the dative and plural, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'handum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Twa (<em>duru</em>) #### hie gesawon on ðære cyrcan ond wæs seo suþ duru sume dæle mare — Two doors they saw in the church, and the south door was somewhat larger",
        "correctAnswer": "dura",
        "explanation":"Here 'duru' is a u-declension noun in the nominative and plural, so it takes the 'a' ending to become 'dura'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He ðas foldan asiow sæda manigum (<em>wudu</em>) #### ond wyrta weorulde sceatum — He sowed this land with many seeds, trees and plants in the regions of the world",
        "correctAnswer": "wuda",
        "explanation":"Here 'wudu' is a u-declension noun in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'a' ending to become 'wuda'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðeos wyrt ðe man batrachion ond oðrum naman clufwyrt nemneþ, biþ cenned on sandigum landum ond on (<em>feld</em>) #### — This herb which is called batrachion, and by another name buttercup, is produced on sandy lands and in fields",
        "correctAnswer": "feldum",
        "explanation":"Here 'feld' is a u-declension noun in the dative and plural, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'feldum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo dreorige modor astreaht æt þæs halgan apostoles fotum, biddende þæt he hire (<em>sunu</em>) #### arærde, swa swa he dyde þa wydewan Drusianam — The afflicted mother prostrated at the holy apostle's feet, praying that he would rear up her son, as he did the widow Drusiana",
        "correctAnswer": "sunu",
        "explanation":"Here 'sunu' is a u-declension noun in the accusative and singular, so it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "suna",
                "explanation": "Here 'sunu' is directly receiving the action of the verb arærde, even though it comes before it. This makes it accusative, so it takes no ending and remains 'sunu'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ge-edstaðela nu þas deorwurðan gymstanas, ðurh ðinra engla (<em>hand</em>) ####, þæt ðas nytenan menn þine mihta oncnawon — Restore now these precious gems through your angels' hands, that these ignorant men may acknowledge your powers",
        "correctAnswer": "handa",
        "explanation":"Here 'hand' is a u-declension noun in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'a' ending to become 'handa'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God bebead Moyse þæt he ond eall Israhela folc sceoldon offrian Gode an lamb anes geares, ond mearcian mid þæm blode rode-tacn on heora (<em>duru</em>) #### ond oferslegum — God commanded Moses that he and all the people of Israel should offer a lamb of one year to God, and mark with the blood the sign of the cross on their door-posts and lintels",
        "correctAnswer": "durum",
        "explanation":"Here 'duru' is a u-declension noun in the dative and plural, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'durum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie on (<em>wudu</em>) #### ond on westenum and on scræfum hie hyddon ond digledon — They in woods and in wastelands and in caves concealed and hid themselves",
        "correctAnswer": "wudum",
        "explanation":"Here 'wudu' is a u-declension noun in the dative and plural, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'wudum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic wille ðæt ælc man sind his huntnoþes wyrðe on wuda ond on (<em>feld</em>) #### on his agenan — I will that every man have the right to hunt in wood and in open country on his own property",
        "correctAnswer": "felda",
        "explanation":"Here 'feld' is a u-declension noun in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'a' ending to become 'felda'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo þa gelyfde his wordum, ond wearð mid (<em>cild</em>) #### — She believed his words and became with child",
        "correctAnswer": "cilde",
        "explanation":"Here 'cild' is an r-plural noun in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'e' ending to become 'cilde'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sceawa nu on anum (<em>æg</em>) #### hu ðæt hwite ne biþ gemenged to ðam geolcan ond biþ hwæðere an æg — Look now on an egg, how the white is not mingled with the yolk, and yet it is one egg",
        "correctAnswer": "æge",
        "explanation":"Here 'æg' is an r-plural noun in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'e' ending to become 'æge'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He gefullode ðone wulf ond geworhte to (<em>lamb</em>) #### — He baptised the wulf and made it a lamb",
        "correctAnswer": "lambe",
        "explanation":"Here 'lamb' is an r-plural noun in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'e' ending to become 'lambe'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ne on-foo of huse ðinum (<em>cealf</em>) #### — I will take no calves from your house",
        "correctAnswer": "cealfru",
        "explanation":"Here 'cealf' is an r-plural noun in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'ru' ending to become 'cealfru'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Nu todæg Godes gelaðung geond ealne ymbhwyrft mærsað þæra eadigra (<em>cild</em>) #### freols-tide — Now today God's church throughout all the globe celebrates the festival of the blessed children",
        "correctAnswer": "cildra",
        "explanation":"Here 'cild' is an r-plural noun in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ra' ending to become 'cildra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Genim hænne (<em>æg</em>) #### geolocan ond hwites sealtes godne dael, men eal tosomne — Take the yoke of a hen's egg and a good portion of white salt, mix all together",
        "correctAnswer": "æges",
        "explanation":"Here 'æg' is an r-plural noun in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'es' ending to become 'æges'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He is Lamb gehaten for ðære unscæððignysse (<em>lamb</em>) #### gecyndes ond wæs unscyldig — He is called Lamb, from the innocence of the lamb's nature; and was guiltless",
        "correctAnswer": "lambes",
        "explanation":"Here 'lamb' is an r-plural noun in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'es' ending to become 'lambes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Me ymbhringdon mænige (<em>cealf</em>) #### — Many cattle surrounded me",
        "correctAnswer": "cealfru",
        "explanation":"Here 'cealf' is an r-plural noun in the nominative and plural, so it takes the 'ru' ending to become 'cealfru'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þæt godspel cweð þæt Rachel beweop hire (<em>cild</em>) #### ond nolde beon gefrefrod — The gospel says, that Rachel wept for her children, and would not be comforted",
        "correctAnswer": "cildra",
        "explanation":"Here 'cild' is an r-plural noun in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'ra' ending to become 'cildra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þam cildum ic bead þæt hie gehyrsume wæron (<em>fæder</em>) #### ond modor to halwendum mynegungum —  Children I bade that they be obedient to the salutary admonitions of father and mother",
        "correctAnswer": "fæder",
        "explanation":"Here 'fæder' is a family noun in the genitive and singular, so it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hieronimus se halga sacerd awrat ænne pistol be forðsiðe þære eadigan Marian to sumum halgan mædene ond to hire (<em>modor</em>) #### Paulam — Jerome the holy priest wrote an epistle on the decease of the blessed Mary, to a holy maiden and to her mother Paula",
        "correctAnswer": "meder",
        "explanation":"Here 'modor' is a family noun in the dative and singular, so the vowels change from 'o' to 'e' to become 'meder'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se ðe ðis hylt, he bið Godes bearn, and Crist, and ealle halige men ðe Gode geðeoð, beoð his broðra and his (<em>sweostor</em>) #### — He who observes this is a child of God, and Christ, and all holy persons who thrive to God, are his brothers and his sisters.",
        "correctAnswer": "sweostra",
        "explanation":"Here 'sweostor' is a family noun in the accusative and plural, so it loses its final 'o' and gains the 'a' ending to become 'sweostra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Soðlice seo cwen Triphonia gesohte ðæs halgan sacerdes fet Iustines mid biterum tearum ond hire (<em>dohtor</em>) #### Cyrilla samod, biddende þæs halgan fulluhtes — But the queen Tryphonia, together with her daughter Cyrilla, sought the feet of the holy priest Justin with bitter tears, praying for holy baptism",
        "correctAnswer": "dohtor",
        "explanation":"Here 'dohtor' is a family noun in the nominative and singular, so it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Mine (<em>broðor</em>) ####, ne beo ge afyrhte, cumað ond eower nan him ne ondræde ða scortan tintregunga — My brothers, be you not afraid, come, and let none of you dread short torments",
        "correctAnswer": "broðra",
        "explanation":"Here 'broðor' is a family noun in the nominative and plural, so it loses its final 'o' and gains the 'a' ending to become 'broðra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic manode (<em>fæder</em>) #### þæt hie mid steore Godes eges heora cildra geðeawodon — I exhorted fathers to bring up their children in the fear of God",
        "correctAnswer": "fæderas",
        "explanation":"Here 'fæder' is a family noun in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "fædera",
                "explanation": "Here 'fæder' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'manode' making it accusative. Unlike other family nouns, the accusative plural ending for 'fæder' is 'as', not 'a', so it becomes 'fæderas'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se ylca God þe gesceop Adam mid his handum, he gescypð ælces mannes lichaman on his (<em>modor</em>) #### innoðe — The same God who created Adam with his hands, created every man's body in his mother's womb",
        "correctAnswer": "modor",
        "explanation":"Here 'modor' is a family noun in the genitive and singular, so it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Adam þa wæs wunigende on þisum life mid geswince, ond he and his wif ða bearn gestryndon, ægðer suna ond (<em>dohtor</em>) #### — Adam then was continuing in this life with toil, and he and his wife begat children, both sons and daughters",
        "correctAnswer": "dohtra",
        "explanation":"Here 'dohtor' is a family noun in the accusative and plural, so it loses its final 'o' and gains the 'a' ending to become 'dohtra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þa dælde se casere þæt Iudeisce rice on feower, ond sette ðærto feower (<em>broðor</em>) #### ða sind gecwedene æfter Greciscum gereorde, tetrarche — The emperor then divided the Jewish kingdom into four, and placed therein four brothers, who, according to the Greek tongue, are called 'tetrarchs'",
        "correctAnswer": "broðra",
        "explanation":"Here 'broðor' is a family noun in the accusative and plural, so it loses its final 'o' and gains the 'a' ending to become 'broðra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He hæfde gefeormod (<em>fot</em>) #### ond handa — He had devoured feet and hands",
        "correctAnswer": "fet",
        "explanation":"Here 'fot' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'fet'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ banece genim tuning wyrt beolone wealwyrt ealde grut ond eced, heorotes smera oþþe gate oþþe (<em>gos</em>) ####, meng tosomne lege þonneon — For bone ache, take white veratrum, dwarf elder, spent malt, and vinegar, hart’s fat or goat’s or goose’s, mix together, then apply",
        "correctAnswer": "gose",
        "explanation":"Here 'gos' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'e' ending to become 'gose'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "goses",
                "explanation": "While 'gos' is in the genitive and singular, it is a feminine noun, and so takes the feminine 'e' ending, not the masculine 'es' ending, to become 'gose'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif wyrm ete þa (<em>toð</em>) #### genim ofer geare holen rinde ond eoforþrotan moran wel on swa hatumhafa on muþe swa hat swa þu hatost mæge — If a worm eats the teeth take holly bark more than a year old and the root of stemless carline thistle, boil in such hot water, hold in the mouth as hot as you can",
        "correctAnswer": "teð",
        "explanation":"Here 'toð' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'teð'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We us gegadrian to his halgan gelaðunge, þæt ure naman beon awritene on lifes (<em>boc</em>) #### mid his gecorenum — We gather us to his holy congregation that our names may be written in the book of life with his chosen",
        "correctAnswer": "bec",
        "explanation":"Here 'boc' is in the dative and singular so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'bec'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He his wæs (<em>freond</em>) #### gefylled — He was deprived of his friends",
        "correctAnswer": "freonda",
        "explanation":"Here 'freond' is in the genitive and plural so it gains the 'a' ending to become 'freonda'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þis geat ne bið nanum (<em>mann</em>) #### geopenod, ac se Hlaford ana færð inn þurh þæt geat — This gate shall be opened to no man, for the Lord only will go in by that gate",
        "correctAnswer": "menn",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the dative and singular so the root-vowel changes from 'a' to 'e' to become 'menn'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ne lufie (<em>mus</em>) #### ond flæa forðam ðe hie sind flesclicu nytenu nes men — I don't like mice and fleas because they are carnal creatures, not men",
        "correctAnswer": "mys",
        "explanation":"Here 'mus' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'u' to 'y' to become 'mys'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif ðu gemete ðines (<em>feond</em>) #### oxan oððe assan, lad hine to him — If you meet your enemy's ox or donkey, you lead them back to him",
        "correctAnswer": "feondes",
        "explanation":"Here 'feond' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'es' ending to become 'feondes'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "feonde",
                "explanation": "While 'feond' is in the genitive and singular, it is a masculine noun, and so takes the masculine 'es' ending, not the feminine 'e' ending, to become 'feondes'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ (<em>lus</em>) #### acrind ond hwon wermod gecnua on ealu sele drincan — For lice, grind oak bark and a little wormwood in ale, give to drink",
        "correctAnswer": "lusum",
        "explanation":"Here 'lus' is in the dative and plural so it gains the 'um' ending to become 'lusum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðone æðeling on ðære (<em>burg</em>) #### metton, ðar se cyning ofslægen læg — They found the prince in the walled town where the king lay slain",
        "correctAnswer": "byrg",
        "explanation":"Here 'burg' is in the dative and singular so the root-vowel changes from 'u' to 'y' to become 'byrg'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ ealcum heardum swile oððe geswelle gebeat hunan meng wiþ rysele oððe (<em>gate</em>) #### horn gebærned ond wiþ wætergemenged lege on — For every hard swelling and pustule beat horehound, mix with grease or burned goat’s horn mixed with water and apply",
        "correctAnswer": "gate",
        "explanation":"Here 'gat' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'e' ending to become 'gate'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ðæt gehate ðæt ic heonon nelle fleon (<em>fot</em>) #### trym — I vow that I will not flee hence one footstep",
        "correctAnswer": "fotes",
        "explanation":"Here 'fot' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'es' ending to become 'fotes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Feawa he awrat be his menniscnysse, forðam þe þa ðry oðre godspelleras genihtsumlice be þam heora (<em>boc</em>) #### setton — He wrote few things of his human nature, because the three other evangelists had composed their books abundantly concerning that.",
        "correctAnswer": "bec",
        "explanation":"Here 'boc' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'bec'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt inwitspell Abraham sægde (<em>freond</em>) #### sinum — Abraham told that tale of woe to his friends",
        "correctAnswer": "freondum",
        "explanation":"Here 'freond' is in the dative and plural so it gains the 'um' ending to become 'freondum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se hundredman sende his (<em>freond</em>) #### to him — The centurion sent his friends to him",
        "correctAnswer": "friend",
        "explanation":"Here 'friend' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'eo' to 'ie' to become 'friend'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Forðam ðe Crist is ealra hlaforda Hlaford, ægðer ge (<em>mann</em>) #### ge ealra gesceafta — For Christ is Lord of all lords, both of men and of all creatures",
        "correctAnswer": "manna",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the genitive and plural so it gains the 'a' ending to become 'manna'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif he us deadlicum (<em>mann</em>) #### ærist and þæt ece lif behete, hwa wolde þonne his behatum gelyfan? — If he to us mortal men had promised resurrection and life eternal, who would have believed in his promises?",
        "correctAnswer": "mannum",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the dative and plural so it gains the 'um' ending to become 'mannum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ weartum, genim hundes micgean ond (<em>mus</em>) #### blod, meng tosomne, smire mid þa weartan ond hie gewitaþ sona aweg — For warts, take hound's urine and mouse's blood, mix together, anoint the warts with it and they will soon go away",
        "correctAnswer": "muse",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'e' ending to become 'muse'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>feond</em>) #### his diorlingas duguþum stepte — The fiend decked his favourites with honours",
        "correctAnswer": "feond",
        "explanation":"Here 'feond' is the subject and singular so it takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]